Nathanael Greene Papers 1777-1780 Mss.B.G83
American Philosophical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1777-1780; 3 lin. feet
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 10; 2pp.; Hubbard, Nehemiah (Box 3)
    Hartford - Acknowledging letters of 29th and 31st ult. Has secured all the duck possible without money. Orders of His Excellency, the Commander-in-chief, to the Governor, to remove one regiment to any town in the State (Connecticut). Col. Moylan's arrival in the State with a mistaken notion of the extent of his authority. Will discharge all the teams unless they agree to serve the next campaign.
    i, 37
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 11; 1p.; Hubbard, Nehemiah (Box 3)
    Hartford - Enclosing a copy of an account presented to Mr. Hubbard for payment - is he to pay it? Also encloses returns.
    ix, 70
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 24; 2pp.; Hubbard, Nehemiah (Box 3)
    Hartford - Enclosing Col. Moylan's and Col. Sheldon's returns for accoutrements and repairs for their regiments. Mentions articles he is unable to furnish. Col. Webb desires to have forwarded to Morristown a pipe of wine and some loaf-sugar, for himself and Gen. Greene; roads almost impassable, but will send them forward soon by some trusty person. Blank certificates not yet arrived. Uncertainty of the post.
    i, 39
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 29; 2pp.; Hubbard, Nehemiah (Box 3)
    Hartford - Wrote him on the 24th inst., enclosing a copy of certain returns. Hears through Major Talmage that a large quantity of horse furniture is at Springfield, which could be obtained on order. Obstacles in the way of obtaining carts. Terms on which he has engaged the teams. Debt Capt. Starr wishes to pay to an express-ride.
    i, 38
  - to George Gray, 1779 April 10; 1p.; Hudson, J. (Box 3)
    Order to repair a gun of 2d Virginia Regiment.
    xii, 74
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 September 18; 1p.; Hughes, John (Box 3)
    West Point - Enclosing weekly return of the camp equipage. Fifty-seven tents returned unfit for service.
    iii, 49
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 3; 1p.; Hughes, John (Box 3)
    Has engaged a number of teams. Desires Gen. Greene's orders as to their rations, as he does not consider the recommendation or orders of Mr. Lewis binding on him, the brigade, or any part thereof.
    i, 42
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 20; 1p.; Humphreys, Whitehead (Box 3)
    Stating the terms on which he would make axes for use of the army.
    viii, 63
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 August 20; 1p.; Hunter, Mtn. (Box 3)
    Warwick - Concerning a verbal order given some time before by Gen. Greene to supply a certain Mr. Counter with three horses, a saddle and bridle. Col. Hay will not replace them without a written order from Gen. Greene.
    x, 10
  - to Samuel A. Otis, 1779 February 6; 1p.; Hunter, William (Box 3)
    Boston - Receipt for two silver cups which he promises to deliver to General Greene.
    ix, 87
  - to Samuel A. Otis, 1779 February 7; 1p.; Hunter, William (Box 3)
    Boston - Receipt for the sum of £15.
    ix, 88
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 13; 1p.; Huntingdon, Samuel (Box 3)
    Philadelphia - Enclosing Act of Congress of the 12th inst. respecting the rank of certain men in the army.
    ix, 71
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 19; 1p.; Huntingdon, Samuel (Box 3)
    Philadelphia - Enclosing three Acts of Congress for reforming and incorporating the eleven companies of artificers and making further provisions for them as specified in the several acts. Capt. Pendleton's faithfulness in this business and his subsequent sickness.
    i, 43
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 8; 1p.; Huntingdon, Samuel (Box 3)
    Philadelphia - Enclosing Act of Congress, directing payment to be made by the Quartermaster-General or his deputy for horses killed in battle, belonging to officers whose duty it is to be on horseback.
    i, 44
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 14; 1p.; Huntingdon, Samuel (Box 3)
    Philadelphia - Enclosing Act of Congress of 11th inst. with directions concerning the accounts of supplies to be furnished the troops of the convention of Saratoga.
    viii, 65
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 31; 1p.; Irvine, William, 1741-1804 (Box 4)
    Camp near Morristown - Congratulating Mrs. Greene and the General, and wishing them joy. Has written the State Commissary to send all the soap he can spare.
    i, 49
  - to George Gray, 1779 April 7; 1p.; Jackson (Dr.) (Box 4)
    Order to have his horse shod and four rivets made for his desk.
    xii, 79
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 15; 1p.; Jamison, Adam (Box 4)
    Middlebrook - Has requested a Court of Inquiry that the accusations of one Geo. Hook, wagoner, against himself may be disproved.
    vii, 97
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 21; 1p.; Jamison, Adam (Box 4)
    Middlebrook - Enclosing the sentence of the Court of Inquiry, which he trusts will give Gen. Greene full satisfaction.
    v, 51
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 5; 2pp.; Jay, James (Box 4)
    Fishkill - Concerning a horse which he bought from Col. Hay, who sometime after, told him that he never rode him thirty miles without his falling lame. Considered it a joke, having several times ridden him more than that without the least injury. Has kept the horse so far in reserve for Gen. Greene, but he is perfectly free to take or leave him after consulting with Col. Hay.
    i, 48
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 22; 1p.; Jay, John (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Acknowledging letter of 18th inst. and promising to transmit the determination of Congress on the subject.
    i, 47
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 1; 1p.; Jay, John (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Enclosing copy of Act of Congress directing the payment of sundry amounts to the inhabitants of New York, for provisions supplied and services performed immediately after the loss of Fort Montgomery. Execution of this act to be carried out at once, the sums having been due over a year.
    i, 46
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 19; 1p.; Jay, John (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Transmitting him a copy of an Act of Congress of the 11th inst., making further provision for officers in Gen. Greene's department.
    v, 27
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 20; 1p.; Jay, John (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Introducing Lt. Col. Morris, who, having left Gen. Sullivan's family, desires a place in Gen. Greene's.
    v, 38
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 24; 3pp.; Jay, John (Box 4)
    Smith's Clove - Concerning a law passed by the Legislature of the State of New Jersey for the express purpose of taxing the assistant and deputy quartermasters-general; likely to produce disagreeable consequences; this arbitrary imposition cannot fail to drive out of the department every capable and trustworthy man. Mr. Furman has already resigned and Col. Cox and Mr. Pettit only wait to know the issue of a memorial presented to Congress. Should they resign, will not be responsible for the terrible consequences, neither will he take any fee or reward for his services in that event. Has heard some doubts about the holding of his command. If, by serving on the staff, he should lose the honors of the line he could never be repaid, nor could he ever serve in the department during another campaign.
    vi, 96
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 30; 2pp.; Jay, John (Box 4)
    New Windsor - Acknowledging favor of the 16th. Thinks the act granting certain privileges to wagoners in the public service will be attended with many advantages; explains why he thinks the other act relating to wagon-hire impracticable.
    vi, 98
  - to Col. Hollingsworth, 1779 May 12; 1p.; Johnson, Thomas, 1732-1819 (Box 4)
    Annapolis - Informing him of the narrow escape of Capt. Hanson, who encountered certain armed vessels in the bay and put back to Annapolis. Report by Mr. Robinson of a schooner bound to sea chased by a fleet of between twenty and thirty sail; heard nothing further.
    vii, 80
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 8; 2pp.; Johnston, Francis (Box 4)
    Cross Roads, Chester Co. - Introducing Major Dick to his particular notice, and requesting as a personal favor that he may be given the late Col. Sheriff's place in the county of Chester.
    i, 45
  - to Any Continental Smith, 1779 April 2; 1p.; Johnston, James (Box 4)
    Auditor's Office - Order to shoe his horse.
    xii, 80
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 24; 1p.; Johnston, James and Joseph Howell (Box 4)
    Auditor's Office - Asking that the proper orders be given for forwarding a box of warrants.
    vi, 7
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 9; 1p.; Joyce, William (Box 4)
    Middletown - Acknowledging favor of 6th inst. Has half promised his services to a privateer bark sailing the latter end of the month; will get three shares of the profits. However, will leave the privateer and undertake with Gen. Greene if he will pay a certain price.
    x, 51
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 30; 1p.; Kearse, Benjamin (Box 4)
    Smith's Tavern - Orders to furnish Col. Hay with public wagons sufficient to remove his family and effects. A large covering party necessary to protect them from the enemy.
    vi, 77
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 February 23; 1p.; Kelso, Robert (Box 4)
    Morristown - Enclosing Maerschalk's receipt for two branches and twenty-one tin sconces, on behalf of Col. Abeel.
    iv, 64
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 26; 1p.; Kemper, Daniel (Box 4)
    Asking for teams in which to send the clothing to Gen. Sullivan's troops, according to His Excellency's directions.
    v, 76
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 4; 4pp.; Kingsland, Eliza (Box 4)
    Albany - A pathetic letter, setting forth various incidents of her life and beseeching that her husband may not be recalled to his regiment, as his work is the only thing which supports herself and her three little children; to follow a camp is far worse than death to her.
    ii, 74
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 October 13; 1p.; Kinnan, Peter (Box 4)
    Ringwood - Announcing that there are two bridges on the public road from Pompton to Ringwood, one of which is entirely useless and unfit for service, the other likely to break down any day; such an accident would mean a fearful delay of provisions and other necessaries. Overseers of the roads pay no attention to his requests; wishes directions as to what to do; makes suggestions and refers him to Mr. Erskine.
    i, 50
  - to George Gray, 1779 January 22; 1p.; Kirkpatrick, Abraham, 1749-1817 (Box 4)
    Desiring his horse be shod all round.
    i, 51
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 20; 1p.; Knox, Henry (Box 4)
    Camp, Fredericksburg - Begging him to give directions to his deputy at Springfield to pay for such lumber and coal as may be wanted for the use of the ordnance mills at that place.
    i, 52
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 25; 1p.; Knox, Henry (Box 4)
    Pluckemin - Promising to send all tentmakers to Morristown. Mrs. Knox and the young ladies send their compliments to Mrs. Greene and the ladies.
    i, 54
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 13; 1p.; Knox, Henry (Box 4)
    West Point - The desire of His Excellency that the preparations of the five ships at New London shall be stopped. Mentions the matter so that he (Knox) may send such orders to Mr. Hubbard as he thinks proper. Asks for news of winter quarters.
    i, 53
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 28; 1p.; Kościuszko, Tadeusz, 1746-1817 (Box 4)
    Recommending certain workers as the most active and honest, and therefore entitled to have the preference in the new arrangement. Has sent the Commander-in-chief the plans of Fort Putnam; desires his opinion.
    i, 55
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 November 3; 2pp.; Larzelier, Abraham, and J. Parsell (Box 4)
    Fishkill - Protest made by certain artificers against the prices of provisions, and also against the exorbitant wages paid to certain other men.
    iii, 5 1/2
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 November 3; 1p.; Larzelier, Abraham, and J. Parsell (Box 4)
    Fishkill - From certain artificers, setting forth the depreciation of money, the dearness of provisions and the higher wages received by mechanics at other places. Have the interest of their country at heart and only desire what will reasonably support them.
    iii, 6
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 26; 1p.; Lawrence, John (Box 4)
    Morristown - Enclosing a summons for Mr. Clark to attend a general court-martial on Monday next at Morristown, on the case of Col. Howard.
    i, 56
  - to George Gray, 1778 December 31; 1p.; Lawson, Benjamin (Box 4)
    Order to shoe Mr. Carny's horse.
    xii, 85
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 12; 2pp.; Lewis, Joseph (Box 4)
    Smith's Tavern - Owing to the illness of Mr. Lewis, was obliged to call in the aid of the country to forward the provisions. Now that he is restored to health, will send Mr. Abeel word to leave the business entirely to him. Begs that he and MR. Abeel will lay aside their disputes and prejudices in order to promote the public welfare.
    vi, 51
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 7; 1p.; Lewis, Joseph (Box 4)
    Morristown - About forty horses in his district; not possible to recruit them fast enough to keep up the almost hourly exchange of horses at his post. Abuse of horse-flesh by the expresses, hired at Philadelphia; better for the Continent to pay each express $ 40.00 per day and let him keep his own horse. Court of Inquiry still sitting; not yet finished examining the evidences against him [Lewis].
    iii, 82
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 7; 1p.; Lewis, Joseph (Box 4)
    Good saw-mill standing still for want of a saw; can Col. Abeel spare one?
    viii, 64
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 13; 1p.; Lewis, Joseph (Box 4)
    Morristown - Wishes to have Gen. Greene's orders for the number of boards to be furnished each brigade.
    ix, 74
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 27; 1p.; Lewis, Joseph (Box 4)
    In want of an express to go to Elizabethtown and Newark on business, by request of Col. Furman; would like him therefore to send one to his office.
    i, 58
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 28; 1p.; Lewis, Joseph (Box 4)
    Morristown - Question of the proper pay of a two-horse team per day. Wishes his directions on that point, and also on whether it is proper for him to settle their certificates.
    i, 59
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 29; 1p.; Lewis, Joseph (Box 4)
    Morristown - Enclosing an estimate of expenses incurred in employing the civil authority of Morris county, and also in the Staten Island expedition.
    i, 57
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 8; 3pp.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Question of procuring boards and planks. Places before him the case of a Mr. Smith, whose house has been so long needed as a station by American troops that he has lost the income of a year's produce; wishes to know what compensation should be made him. Encloses return of articles at this post.
    i, 63
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 9; 3pp.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Unpardonable delay of Gen. Greene's expresses. Number and condition of the bateaux at hand. Will want to employ at least one company of bateaux men during the coming winter; discusses means of providing them with clothes, as they are literally naked. Money nearly expended; would like about $ 30,000; in case of the arrival of troops, has barracks in Albany for 440 men and at Schenectady and Saratoga for as many more.
    i, 61
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 12; 7pp.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Acknowledging favors of 19th, 20th and 26th utl. Large preparations in his department rendered unnecessary by Gen. Schuyler's instructions. Difficulty of getting forage. Officers' horses consume too much. The few tools received so far from Springfield, very ill made and inadequate for the work. Wages of shipwrights. Inducements necessary to obtain bateaux men. If his assistants' wages are not raised they will quit. Principal articles needed. Enclosing returns for the last month.
    iv, 65, 66
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 5; 1p.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Acknowledging favor of the 15th ult. Prepared at all points for the expedition in his quarter; troops will march on the following Monday. Pestered for cash.
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 10; 1p.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Camp at Smith's Clove - Gen. Washington has written to Gen. Clinton to be in readiness for a certain movement. Orders him to apply to Gen. Clinton to Ascertain his wants. This business requiring utmost dispatch.
    vi, 41
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 September 27; 2pp.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    West Point - Desiring him not to engage in building his store until the garrison at West Pint is finished with a sufficient quantity of boards to barrack the troops, which must be sent on with all speed. Just received an order from His Excellency, Gen. Washington, to order down all the flatboats from Albany; not a moment's time is to be lost, as the General is in hourly expectation of Count d'Estaing's arrival, when the boats will be wanted immediately.
    iv, 34
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 October 5; 1p.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Promising him all the boards he can spare, but obliged to keep enough to employ his carpenters, and also to build a cooper's shop.
    iii, 52
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 6; 2pp.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Acknowledging the receipt of $ 200,000, which is only enough to pay for money borrowed. Under the necessity therefore of sending Mr. Vosborough for a further immediate supply, as he cannot possibly purchase upon credit. If $ 500,000 is sent, imagines that will be sufficient till the following spring. Question of clothes; poorly made in Philadelphia, and very dear, one suit of them amounting to one-third of a bateaux man's yearly pay.
    i, 64
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 7; 1p.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Acknowledging favor of 4th inst. Has sent to Fishkill sixteen bateaux and will send forty more in the course of a fortnight. Boats from Mohock river will also be sent to Fishkill. Every carpenter busy working on boats. Sends Col. Hay all the boards he can spare. Amount of oakum being sent to Fishkill. Will use every exertion to regain possession of his native city.
    iii, 83
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 11; 1p.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - In a few days will have every board which the country can afford. Desires any vessels which Col. Hay can spare. In the event of regaining possession of New York, would be glad of the position there of quartermaster. Not a tent in the department.
    i, 60
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 22; 3pp.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Acknowledging favors of 17th inst. The paper which Gen. Greene desires is not in his possession. Declines to mention the terms of his future service, being persuaded that his former letter on that subject was not agreeable. Thinks, however, that the business of his department has been transacted at a much cheaper rate than any other; can prove this. Quartermaster-General's appointment not a profitable one in his district. Various supplies of boats and their materials sent to Col. Hay; building six bateaux daily.
    iii, 84
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 11; 1p.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Transmitting returns. Asking him to forward the Treasurer's letter and procure him an order for the money, as he is distressed for want of cash. Will attend to his orders respecting grain and tar.
    ix, 72
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 21; 1p.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Asking for an order on the Board of War for 1000 green hides, as leather is necessary and scarce. Must have money or all business will come to a stand still.
    ix, 73
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 4; 3pp.; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844 (Box 4)
    Albany - Acknowledging letter of 19th ult. Promises to adopt the mode he prescribes for acquiring an exact account of moneys due from the department. Has mentioned it already to some of his creditors in the city; they declined to accept of any certificate in lieu of money, even threatening a prosecution. People distressed for money to pay their taxes; and those living at a distance will certainly not bring in their accounts to receive only a promise of payment. Those driven from their habitations in 1777, demand payment for boards, etc., taken from them on the retreat. His assistants dissatisfied, and properly so, with their payment; they will leave unless something is done. Desires to know the truth of a report tat a Resolution of Congress allows the staff clothing. Complains bitterly against the rate at which he has been taxed, as he has no visible property on earth and has been taxed merely for doing Gen. Greene's business.
    i, 62
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 12; 1p.; Lind, Arthur (Box 4)
    Ordered by Col. Heth to proceed immediately to Pompton for his baggage; applies for a horse to go on the above business. Also asks for sufficient power to impress a wagon at Pompton.
    vii, 78 and 78a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 10; 3pp.; Livingston, Abraham (Box 4)
    Charleston, S.C. - Acknowledging favor of 5th ult. covering an order of Congress for the procuration of a quantity of rough rice and vessels for the transportation thereof. Will proceed to the purchase at the proper time, but must have a supply of money.
    i, 66
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 10, 11, 27; 7pp.; Livingston, Abraham (Box 4)
    Charleston - Duplicate of above. Charleston - Is in treaty for the chartering of two ships and a brig. Expenses incidental thereto. Charleston - Acknowledging letter of 29th ult. Number of ships engaged. Depends on Gen. Greene's generosity to prevent his being involved in difficulties, by furnishing him immediately with a sufficient sum of money.
    ix, 75, 75a, 75b
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 26; 2pp.; Livingston, Abraham (Box 4)
    Charleston - Acknowledging letter of August 31 covering an award respecting the brigantine Sally. The vessel, after lying the whole summer as a prison-ship, has been returned in a shocking condition. Will cost a large sum of money, even fitting her out in the most frugal manner. State of his health makes him desirous of closing his public transactions, and therefore requests Gen. Greene to appoint some other person in his place.
    i, 67
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 5; 4pp.; Livingston, William, 1723-1790 (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Acknowledging favor of October 21, and congratulating him on the latest addition to his family. The extravagance of Philadelphia. Suggests a loan from some foreign power to raise the credit of the money. Enemy relying on our money losing its credit. Policy of New Jersey exceedingly corrupt. Mentions the address of the Assembly to the Governor of New York as a serious matter to the country. Necessity of the States confederating. The conduct of Congress. A shocking spectacle of corruption and deception. Surprised at the conduct of Massachusetts in returning the same members; dangerous trusting the same people too long. Refers him to Gen. Wadsworth for the history of the times. Quotes Lee as speaking loudly against His Excellency, saying he is an old woman, has no stability, etc. P.S. November 8 - A report that Jamaica is taken.
    i, 65
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 14; 2pp.; Livingston, William, 1723-1790 (Box 4)